有种极其寻常的错误，
It is an extremely common mistake,
那就是，人们认为作家的想象力是台永动机，
people think the writer's
imagination is always at work,
他永远可以供应
that he's constantly inventing
an endless supply
事件和篇章，
of incidents and episodes,
他能简简单单，凭空编出故事来。
that he simply dreams up his
stories out of thin air.
事实正相反。
In point of fact, the
opposite is true.
一旦公众知道你是作家，
Once the public knows
you're a writer,
他们就把角色和事件带给你
they bring the characters
and events to you
只要你擦亮双眼
and as long as you maintain
your ability to look
并仔细聆听，
and to carefully listen,
那些故事会继续...
these stories will continue to...
住手！住手！别！别这样！
Stop it. Stop it! Don't!
Don't do it!
会继续追寻你一生。
Will continue to seek you
out over your lifetime.
对于这样一位总是讲述他人故事的人来说，
To him who has often told
the tales of others,
也有许多关于他的故事可讲。
many tales will be told.
- 对不起。
- Sorry.
- 没事
- It's all right.
接下来我要在这讲述的事件
The incidents that follow
were described to me
和我听来时完全一样
exactly as I present them here
不过表达的方式将完全出人意料。
and in a wholly unexpected way.
数年前，
A number of years ago,
轻微的“写作热”正折磨着我，
while suffering from a mild case
of "Scribe's Fever,"
那是种当时知识分子常患的精神衰弱症，
a form of neurasthenia common among
the intelligentsia of that time,
于是我决定将八月
I decided to spend
the month of August
花在苏丹特瓦茨山下，那不勒堡的温泉镇里，
in the spa town of Nebelsbad
below the Alpine Sudetenwaltz,
并在布达佩斯大饭店住下，
and had taken up rooms
in the Grand Budapest,
住在那座如画般壮观、一度广为人知的建筑里。
a picturesque, elaborate, and once
widely celebrated establishment.
我想你们之中有人会知道。
I expect some of you will know it.
时值淡季，大饭店又过了时，
It was off season and, by that time,
decidedly out of fashion,
已经开始衰落，
and it had already begun its descent
不断破败，直至损毁。
into shabbiness and
eventual demolition.
我们寥寥数位客人，
What few guests we were
一眼就能认出对方
had quickly come to recognize
one another by sight
是在这宽广住所内居住的仅剩的生灵，
as the only living souls residing
in the vast establishment,
尽管我不相信我们之间的了解，
although I do not believe any acquaintance
among our number had proceeded
超过了那些礼貌的点头，
beyond the polite nods
we exchanged as we passed
于廷廊，
in the Palm Court,
于阿拉伯浴场，
in the Arabian baths,
于石柱索道上擦肩而过。
and onboard the Colonnade Funicular.
看起来，我们都很矜持，
We were a very reserved
group, it seemed,
而且，无一例外地，孤独。
and, without exception, solitary.
也许正是因为这一致的静默，
Perhaps as a result of
this general silence,
我与饭店的门房，一位西欧人，
I had established a casual
and bantering familiarity
随意地熟络起来，一起说笑，
with the hotel's concierge,
a West-continental
他叫简先生，
known only as Monsieur Jean,
一上来又懒散，又真的十分通情达理，让我印象深刻。
who struck one as being, at once, both
lazy and, really, quite accommodating.
我猜他薪水不高。
I expect he was not well paid.
不管怎样，某个夜晚，
In any case, one evening,
当我一如往常，和简先生手肘相贴，站着交谈时，
as I stood conferring elbow-to-elbow
with Monsieur Jean,
我发现一位新来客。
as had become my habit, I noticed
a new presence in our company.
一位身躯矮小，衣着入时的老者，
A small, elderly man,
smartly dressed,
生着张出奇地有神又聪慧的脸庞，
with an exceptionally lively,
intelligent face
带着易于觉察的忧伤。
and an immediately perceptible
air of sadness.
他和我们一样，独身一人，但我不得不说，
He was, like the rest of us, alone,
but also, I must say,
他是第一个，因为深沉而真挚的孤独，
而让我印象深刻的人。
he was the first that struck one
as being deeply and truly lonely.
他和我的病症一样。
A symptom
of my own medical condition as well.
这位有趣的老家伙是谁呀？
Who's this interesting old fellow?
我问简先生。
I inquired of Monsieur Jean.
令我吃惊的是，简先生很是惊讶。
To my surprise,
he was distinctly taken aback.
- 你不知道？
- 他问。
- Don't you know?
- He asked.
你认不出他吗？
Don't you recognize him?
他确实有些眼熟。
He did look familiar.
这是穆斯塔法先生。
他一清早到的。
That's Mr. Moustafa himself.
He arrived earlier this morning.
你们中的旺季常客，
This name will no doubt be familiar
自然熟知这个名字。
to the more seasoned
persons among you.
零.穆斯塔法先生一度是朱波罗卡的首富，
Mr. Zero Moustafa was at one time
the richest man in Zubrowka,
而且仍是布达佩斯大饭店的主人。
and was still indeed the owner
of the Grand Budapest.
他经常在此逗留一个星期，有时多几天，
He often comes and
stays a week or more,
一年至少来三次，但从不在这个季节来。
three times a year at least,
but never in the season.
简先生示意我俯下身。
Monsieur Jean signaled to me
and I leaned closer.
告诉你个秘密。
I'll tell you a secret.
他只住在没有浴室的单床间，
He takes only a single-bed
sleeping room without a bath
就在顶层的后角，
in the rear corner of the top floor
比货梯还小！
and it's smaller than
the service elevator!
众所周知，
It was well known,
零.穆斯塔法购买了几座
Zero Moustafa had purchased
and famously inhabited
欧洲大陆最为奢华的城堡和宫府，居住其内，以此为名。
some of the most lavish castles
and palazzos on the continent.
但是，在这里，在他自己近乎空旷的饭店里，
Yet here, in his own
nearly empty hotel,
他就住在一个仆人的单间里？
he occupied a servant's quarters?
那时，一场附加的室内剧拉开了帷幕...
At that moment, the curtain rose
on a parenthetical, domestic drama...
该死
Shit.
它立刻，完全地吸引了
which required the immediate
and complete attention
简先生的注意，
of Monsieur Jean,
但，说实话，我没怎么留意。
but, frankly, did not
hold mine for long.
然而，
However,
这位奇妙老人的故事过早地被打断，
this premature intermission
in the story of the curious, old man
这让我，正如德国俗话所说，
had left me, as the expression goes,
"心有不甘，"
"gespannt wie ein Flitzebogen,"
也就是说，我坐在凳子的边沿上，
that is, on the edge of my seat,
直到转天早上，
where I remained throughout
the next morning, until,
直到我发觉了命运用着神秘而完全可靠的方式，
in what I have found to be its
mysterious and utterly reliable fashion,
再一次地，闯入了我的生活。
fate, once again,
intervened on my behalf.
我欣赏你的作品。
I admire your work.
您说什么？
I beg your pardon?
我说，我了解并欣赏你绝妙的作品。
I said, I know and admire
your wonderful work.
衷心感谢您，先生。
Thank you most kindly, sir.
简先生有没有或多或少和你讲过
Did Monsieur Jean have a word or two
to share with you
这座建筑那年迈的主人？
about the aged proprietor
of this establishment?
我必须承认，我确实问了关于你的事。
I must confess, I did
myself inquire about you.
简先生无疑很能干，
He's perfectly capable,
of course, Monsieur Jean
但他称不上一流，
but we can't claim he's a first,
或者诚恳点讲，他甚至算不上是二流的门房。
or, in earnest, even
second-rate concierge.
但事情就是这样。
But there it is.
时代变了。
Times have changed.
这儿的温泉浴室很漂亮。
The thermal baths
are very beautiful.
它们和刚建造时一样。
当然，也没法进行修缮。
They were in their first condition.
It couldn't be maintained, of course.
放在当下，有些太颓废派了。
Too decadent for current tastes.
但我还是一样爱这堆迷人的废墟。
But I love it all just the same,
this enchanting old ruin.
冒昧问一句，你为什么要买下它呢？
How did you come to
buy it, if I may ask?
买布达佩斯大饭店。
The Grand Budapest.
我没买。
I didn't.
如果你不仅仅是出于礼貌问我，
If you're not merely being polite,
当然如果是的话请一定要告诉我，
and you must tell me
if that's the case,
不过如果你真的感兴趣的话，
but if it genuinely
does interest you,
我能邀请你今晚和我共进晚餐吗？
may I invite you to
dine with me tonight,
我会非常乐意，事实上这是我的荣幸，
and it will be my pleasure and,
indeed, my privilege to tell you
来为你讲述“我的故事”。虽然这故事不怎么样。
"my story." Such as it is.
两只橄榄烤鸭。
Two ducks roasted with olives.
兔肉，沙拉？
Rabbit, salad?
52年的普伊-儒微，再把干葡萄酒倒一点给我。
Pouilly-Jouvet '52, plus
a split of the brut.
这样时间应该足够了
That should provide us ample time
- 如果我立刻开始讲的话。
- 请务必开始吧。
- if I commence promptly.
- By all means.
好吧，这故事必须，以我们共同朋友的前辈开头。
Well, it begins, as it must, with
our mutual friend's predecessor.
布达佩斯大饭店深受爱戴的第一代门房。
The beloved, original concierge
of The Grand Budapest.
这故事当然是这样开头的...
It begins, of course, with...
- 把桌子搬到窗户边。
- 好的，古斯塔夫先生。
- Bring the table to the window.
- Yes, Monsieur Gustave.
- 把餐盘端到桌子那去。
- 这就去，古斯塔夫先生。
- Bring the tray to the table.
- Right away, Monsieur Gustave.
就放那。
那些刷过了吗？定过型了吗？
Right there.
Have those been brushed and blocked?
- 当然，古斯塔夫先生。
- 把它们装进帽盒里。
- Of course, Monsieur Gustave.
- Pack them in the hat boxes.
- 那是奥伯斯多夫公司的吗？
- 我认为是的，古斯塔夫先生。
- Is that from Oberstdorf & Company?
- I believe so, Monsieur Gustave.
-第二个箱子。谁拿着票呢？
- 在我这，古斯塔夫先生。
- Second trunk. Who has the tickets?
- I do, Monsieur Gustave.
把票给我。
Give them to me.
这些没问题。
在角落等着。
These are in order.
Wait in the corner.
- 我不走了。
- 您说什么？
- I'm not leaving.
- I beg your pardon?
- 我不走了。
- 为什么？
- I'm not leaving.
- Why not?
- 我害怕。
- 怕什么？
- I'm frightened.
- Of what?
我怕这是最后一次见你了。
I fear this may be the last time
we ever see each other.
这怎么可能？
Why on earth would that be the case?
我说不出来，但我就是这么感觉的。
Well, I can't put it into
words, but I feel it.
天哪，你没什么理由离开我们的...
For goodness sake, there's no reason
for you to leave us if you'd...
- 和我走吧。
- 去那个破路兹？
- Come with me.
- To fucking Lutz?
- 求你了。
- 把手给我。
- Please.
- Give me your hand.
没什么好怕的。每次行前你总是焦虑。
You've nothing to fear. You're always
anxious before you travel.
我承认，这次你看起来明显更不舒服。
I admit, you appear to be suffering
a more acute attack on this occasion.
但是，说真的...哦天啊。
你对你的指甲做了什么？
But, truly and honestly... Oh, dear God.
What have you done to your fingernails?
- 你说什么？
- 这天杀的指甲油。
- I beg your pardon?
- This diabolical varnish.
- 这颜色太难看了。
- 你不喜欢？
- The color is completely wrong.
- Don't you like it?
我不是不喜欢。
我都生理不适了。
It's not that I don't like it.
I am physically repulsed.
- 也许这会让你舒服点。
- 什么？别背诗。
- Perhaps this will soothe you.
- What? Don't recite.
- 听听吧。嘘。
- 求你了，别现在背。
- Just listen to the words. Hush.
- Please. Not now.
"我于这片古老高贵又灰暗的松林中求索，
"While questing once in noble wood
of gray, medieval pine,
"行至那被雨露打湿，清凉，飘渺的坟前，
"I came upon a tomb,
rain-slick'd, rubbed-cool, ethereal,
"碑文早已消逝，
"'its inscription long-vanished,
"却在那忧郁的裂缝中..."
"yet still within its
melancholy fissures..."
能为我亮一只蜡烛吗？
Will you light a
candle for me, please?
- 在圣母教堂的圣器室里？
- 我马上就亲自去。
- In the sacristy of Santa Maria?
- I'll see to it myself immediately.
记住，我一直与你同在。
Remember, I'm always with you.
- 我爱你。
- I love you.
能像那样赢得一位女士的芳心很了不起，
It's quite a thing winning
the loyalty of a woman like that
何况还是连续19年。
for 19 consecutive seasons.
- 是的，先生。
- 你知道，她非常喜爱我。
- Yes, sir.
- She's very fond of me, you know.
是的，先生。
Yes, sir.
但我从没见过她那样。
But I've never seen
her like that before.
是的，先生。
No, sir.
她抖得像只在大便的狗。
She was shaking like a shitting dog.
是啊。
Truly.
跑去布鲁克帕兹的圣母教堂
Run to the cathedral of Santa Maria
in Brucknerplatz.
买支朴素的半截蜡烛
Buy one of the plain,
half-length candles
找回四块零钱。
and take back four
Klubecks in change.
在圣堂点亮蜡烛，念一段简短的玫瑰经
Light it in the sacristy,
say a brief rosary
去门德尔家给我买巧克力泡芙。
then go to Mendl's
and get me a courtesan au chocolat.
如果还有钱剩下，赏给瘸腿的擦鞋童。
If there's any money left, give it
to the crippled shoe-shine boy.
- 这就去，先生。
- 等一下。
- Right away, sir.
- Hold it.
- 你是谁？
- 我叫零，先生。我是新来的门童。
- Who are you?
- I'm Zero, sir. The new Lobby Boy.
- 你说你叫零？
- 是的，先生。
- Zero, you say?
- Yes, sir.
我没听过你，也没见过你。谁雇的你？
I've never heard of you, never laid
eyes on you. Who hired you?
- 是莫舍先生，先生。
- 莫舍先生！
- Mr. Mosher, sir.
- Mr. Mosher!
怎么了，古斯塔夫先生？
Yes, Monsieur Gustave?
我是不是可以理解为，你偷偷地雇佣了这位年轻人
Am I to understand you've
surreptitiously hired this young man
做门童？
in the position of a Lobby Boy?
他还在试用期内，当然要等您同意才能雇佣。
He's been engaged for a trial period,
pending your approval, of course.
也许，是的。谢谢，莫舍先生。
Perhaps, yes.
Thank you, Mr. Mosher.
太客气了，古斯塔夫先生。
You're most welcome,
Monsieur Gustave.
你现在要接受正式面试。
You're now going to be
officially interviewed.
我是不是该先去点蜡烛，先生？
Should I go and light
the candle first, sir?
什么？不是。
What? No.
经验？
Experience?
金斯基饭店，在厨房跑腿，六个月。
Hotel Kinski, Kitchen
Boy, six months.
伯利兹饭店，清洁工，三个月。
Hotel Berlitz, Mop and Broom Boy,
three months.
- 那之前我是刷锅的...
- 经验，零。
- Before that I was a Skillet Scrubber...
- Experience, zero.
- 再一次感谢你，古斯塔夫先生。
- 把帽子扶正了，安纳托。
- Thank you again, Monsieur Gustave.
- Straighten that cap, Anatole.
- 我很荣幸，施耐德先生。
- 帽带断了。
- The pleasure's mine, Herr Schneider.
- The strap's busted.
- 这可不行。
- 我完全同意。
- These are not acceptable.
- I fully agree.
- 教育？
- 我学过阅读和拼写。
- Education?
- I studied reading and spelling.
我上了小学。我快要...
I started my primary school.
I almost...
- 教育，零。
- 结果它炸了。
- Education, zero.
- Now it's exploded.
早上好，西塞罗。把该死的水管工叫过来！
Good morning, Cicero.
Call the goddamn plumber!
- 今天下午来吗，古斯塔夫先生？
- 一定到，列柏林女士。
- This afternoon, Monsieur Gustave?
- Without fail, Frau Liebling.
- 这到底是什么鬼东西？
- 别现在问。
- What in hell is this?
- Not now.
家庭？
Family?
零。
Zero.
六楼，伊格。
Six, Igor.
你为什么想当门童？
Why do you want to be a Lobby Boy?
唔，谁不愿意在布达佩斯大饭店当门童呢，先生？
Well, who wouldn't,
at the Grand Budapest, sir?
这名气很大。
It's an institution.
很好。
Very good.
- 一千块钱。
- 我的天啊。
- A thousand Klubecks.
- My goodness.
你曾经是门童吗，先生？
Were you ever a Lobby Boy, sir?
你觉得呢？
What do you think?
唔，我想你总要从某个地方开始的...
Well, I suppose you'd have
to start somewhere...
- 去把破蜡烛点上。
- 好的，先生。
- Go and light the goddamn candle.
- Yes, sir.
就这样，我的人生开始了。
And so, my life began.
培训中的初级门童，
Junior Lobby Boy in-training,
在布达佩斯大饭店，
Grand Budapest Hotel,
古斯塔夫先生严格的要求下进行。
under the strict command
of Monsieur Gustave H.
我是他的小学生，他是我的导师和守护者。
I became his pupil, and he was
to be my counselor and guardian.
什么是门童？
What is a Lobby Boy?
门童要做到完全隐形，又无处不在。
A Lobby Boy's completely
invisible, yet always in sight.
门童要记得客人的忌讳。
A Lobby Boy remembers
what people hate.
门童要料见客人的需求，
A Lobby Boy anticipates
the client's needs
要早于他们提出需求前。
before the needs are needed.
门童，首先，要小心翼翼，不能犯错。
A Lobby Boy is, above all,
discreet to a fault.
我们的客人知道他们心底的有些秘密，
Our guests know their
deepest secrets,
老实说，不如说是见不得人的秘密，
some of which are, frankly,
rather unseemly,
会被我们带到土里。
will go with us to our graves.
- 所以把嘴闭紧了，零。
- 好的，先生。
- So keep your mouth shut, Zero.
- Yes, sir.
目前就这些。
That's all for now.
我开始觉察到，
I began to realize that
many of the hotel's
饭店里最有钱、最尊贵的客人们，是为他而来。
most valued and distinguished guests
came for him.
这看起来是他职责中重要的一环，
It seemed to be an essential part
of his duties,
但我相信他也乐在其中。
but I believe it was
also his pleasure.
筛选她们的标准总是相同。
The requirements were
always the same.
她们都必须富有，
They had to be rich,
年老，
old,
没有安全感，
insecure,
虚荣，
vain,
肤浅，
superficial,
金发，
blonde,
欲求不满。
needy.
为什么选金发？
Why blonde?
因为她们就都是金发的。
Because they all were.
顺便说一句，
He was, by the way,
他是我遇见过的人里，香水喷得最多的一位。
the most liberally perfumed man
I had ever encountered.
未见其人，先闻其香，
The scent announced his approach
from a great distance
且绕梁三日不绝。
and lingered for many minutes
after he was gone.
我一周工作六天，周日也有半天工作，
I worked six days each week
plus a half-day Sunday,
从早上五点，做到午夜。
5:00 AM until just after midnight.
为了保持体力，我们少食多餐。
Our meals were small but frequent,
for stamina.
两顿早餐，两顿午餐，晚餐吃得迟。
Two breakfasts, two lunches
and a late supper.
古斯塔夫先生还在晚间布道。
Monsieur Gustave also delivered
a nightly sermon.
粗鲁仅仅表达了恐惧。
Rudeness is merely the
expression of fear.
人们恐惧无法得到所想。
People fear they won't
get what they want.
只要最为可怕、不讨人喜爱的人被爱，
The most dreadful and unattractive
person only needs to be loved,
他们便会像花儿般绽放。
and they will open
up like a flower.
我想起了一段诗，
I am reminded of a verse,
"绘者的画刷轻触稚嫩脸庞，
"The painter's brush touched
the inchoate face
"用灵巧刷毛的末端，
"by ends of nimble bristles
"初画一笔，色彩便使了无生气的双颊，有了盎然朝气。"
"and with their blush of first color,
rendered her lifeless cheek living."
而他，则在自己的房间独自吃饭。
His own dinner, he took
alone in his room.
我们并不知道大饭店主人的身份。
The identity of the owner of the
hotel was unknown to all of us.
他的秘史，副手卡瓦斯，每个月都会来，
Each month, his emissary,
known as Deputy Kovacs, arrived
检阅账本，传达信息，
to review the books
and convey messages
代表那位神秘的主人。
on behalf of the
mysterious proprietor.
这些时候，古斯塔夫先生和我们的商务经理，
On these occasions, Monsieur Gustave
and our business manager,
贝克先生，都会与卡瓦斯在接待处秘密磋商。
Herr Becker, met with him in private
consultation above Reception.
也是那时，我遇见了阿加莎，
This was also when I met Agatha,
但现在我们不提这个。
but we won't discuss that.
- 干嘛？
- 看。
- What do you want?
- Look.
哪里会有战争？
坦克开至边境
伯爵贵妇死于闺房
天啊。
Dear God.
我很遗憾，先生。
I'm terribly sorry, sir.
- 我们必须去看她。
- 我们必须去吗？
- We must go to her.
- We must?
马上去。她需要我，而我需要你帮我收拾行李等等。
Tout de suite. She needs me, and I need
you to help me with my bags and so on.
- 你多快能收拾好？
- 五分钟。
- How fast can you pack?
- Five minutes.
去吧。再带上瓶26年的普伊-儒微，
Do it. And bring a bottle
of the Pouilly-Jouvet '26
装进冰桶，再带两个杯子，
in an ice bucket with two glasses
这样我们就不用喝餐车里像猫尿的玩意了。
so we don't have to drink the cat
piss they serve in the dining car.
我责备自己。
I blame myself.
她试着告诉我她有坏预感。可我没听。
She tried to tell me she had
a premonition. I didn't listen.
路兹人都会穿上黑衣，
All of Lutz will be
dressed in black,
除了她那可怕的、虚伪的孩子们，
except her own ghastly,
deceitful children
她对他们的憎恶，让她连见面吻都受不了。
whom she loathed
and couldn't bear to kiss hello.
他们肯定跳得和吉普赛人一样开心。
They'll be dancing like gypsies.
人生全无意义，
There's really no point
in doing anything in life,
因为一刹那间就已经完结...
because it's all over in
the blink of an eye...
而且接下来，如你所知，尸斑蓬勃生长。
And, the next thing you know,
rigor mortis sets in.
唉，好人不长命。
Oh, how the good die young.
有幸的话，她会给你的老朋友留几个钱，
With any luck, she's left
a few Klubecks for your old friend,
但只有到了死亡证明落实了才知道。
but one never knows until the ink
is dry on the death certificate.
顺便说一句，她床上功夫不错。
She was dynamite in
the sack, by the way.
古斯塔夫先生，她都84岁了。
She was 84, Monsieur Gustave.
我和更老的也干过。
I've had older.
你年轻时，身边全是菲力牛排，
When you're young,
it's all fillet steak,
但是年华老去，你就得去寻找谢便宜货，
but as the years go by, you have to
move on to the cheaper cuts,
不过我可以接受，因为我喜欢。
which is fine with me,
because I like those.
更加多汁可口，他们这么说。
More flavorful, or so they say.
为什么车要在麦地停下？
Why are we stopping
at a barley field?
唔，你们好啊，小伙子。
Well, hello there, chaps.
请出示证件。
Documents, please.
乐意之至。
With pleasure.
恐怕相片拍得没有真人好看。
It's not a very flattering
portrait, I'm afraid.
我曾经可是大美男。
I was once considered
a great beauty.
你名字的F代表什么？弗瑞兹？弗兰兹？
What does the "F" stand for?
Fritz? Franz?
- 弗兰兹。
- 我就知道！
- Franz.
- I knew it!
他在做鬼脸呢。
He's making a funny face.
亲爱的弗兰兹，那是个三阶工人身份的移民签证。
That's a Migratory Visa with Stage
Three Worker Status, Franz, darling.
他是和我一起的。
He's with me.
请出来一下。
Come outside, please.
等一下。坐下，零。他的证件是合乎程序的。
Now, wait a minute. Sit down, Zero.
His papers are in order.
我亲自和劳役局对照过了。
I cross-referenced them myself with
the Bureau of Labor and Servitude.
你不能因为他是移民就逮捕他。
You can't arrest him simply because
he's a bloody immigrant.
他没做错什么。
He hasn't done anything wrong.
该死的，住手！
Stop it, damn you!
没事的，古斯塔夫先生！不用拦着他们！
Never mind, Monsieur Gustave!
Let them proceed!
嗷！好疼啊！
Ow! That hurts!
你们这些肮脏的，该死的，满脸麻子的法西斯混蛋！
You filthy, goddamn,
pock-marked, fascist assholes!
把你的手从我的门童身上拿开！
Take your hands off my Lobby Boy!
出什么事儿了？
What's the problem?
这太离谱了。
This is outrageous.
这个年轻人在那不勒堡的布达佩斯大饭店为我工作。
The young man works for me at the
Grand Budapest Hotel in Nebelsbad.
古斯塔夫先生？
Monsieur Gustave?
我是汉克斯。
My name is Henckels.
我是父母是沃夫冈.汉克斯.伯格多夫夫妇。
I'm the son of Dr. and Mrs. Wolfgang
Henckels-Bergersdofer.
你还记得我吗？
Do you remember me?
记得一清二楚。太巧了。你是小艾伯特。
I know exactly who you are.
It's uncanny. You're little Albert.
这实在太尴尬了。放开他们。
I'm terribly embarrassed.
Release them.
放开他们。
你的同事没有国籍。
Your colleague is stateless.
他需要申请一个新版特别转移许可，
He'll need to apply for a
revised Special Transit Permit,
但现在很难获得。
which at this point
may be very difficult to acquire.
拿着这个。
Take this.
这是个临时证，但我恐怕只能给你这个了。
It's temporary but it's the
best I can offer, I'm afraid.
令堂怎么样？
And how's your wonderful mother?
- 她很好，谢谢。
- 我仰慕她。
- She's very well, thank you.
- I adore her.
- 代我问好。
- 我会的。
- Send my love.
- I will.
在我还是个孤独的小男孩时，你的同伴对我非常友善。
Your companion was very kind to me
when I was a lonely little boy.
我和我的手下为打扰你而道歉。
My men and I apologize
for disturbing you.
请您原谅，先生。
I beg your pardon, sir.
看见了吗？微弱的文明之光
You see? There are still
faint glimmers of civilization
仍存留在这野蛮的屠场里，这就是人性。
left in this barbaric slaughterhouse
that was once known as humanity.
这确实就是我们这些谦逊，卑微，渺小的人可以提供的...
Indeed, that's what we provide in our
own modest, humble, insignificant...
唉，去他的。
Oh, fuck it.
克罗蒂德，她在哪？带我过去。
Where is she, Clotilde?
Take me to her.
你看起来真好，亲爱的。真的很好。
You're looking so well, darling.
You really are.
入殓师做的很棒。
They've done a marvelous job.
我不知道他们在太平间给你擦了什么乳霜，
I don't know what sort of cream they've
put on you down at the morgue,
我都想要点了。
but I want some.
说实话，你比这几年看起来都好。
Honestly, you look better
than you have in years.
你看起来像个活人。
You look like you're alive.
哎呀，你最后还是把颜色换了。完美。
Oh, you changed it after all.
It's perfect.
- 克罗蒂德？
- 怎么了，古斯塔夫先生？
- Clotilde?
- Oui, Monsieur Gustave?
请给我来一杯无冰凉水。
A glass of chilled water
with no ice, please.
好的，古斯塔夫先生。另外，
瑟奇先生想让您自己去他办公室，他有话和您说。
那好吧。
All right, then.
亲爱的，我不会去很久的。
I shan't be long, darling.
我们被护送着，穿过绿呢门，
We were escorted through
a green baize door,
走下窄窄的服务走廊，进入管家的厨房。
down a narrow service corridor
and into the butler's pantry.
过了一会儿，厨房门被转开，
A moment later, the kitchen
passage swung open
一位身着白衣的矮小仆从突然进了屋。
and a small servant dressed in white
jolted into the room.
我永远也忘不了他的表情。
I've never forgotten
the look on that man's face.
这究竟出什么事儿了？
What the devil is going on?
我自己，一生中，从未踏足这样人家的房子。
I, myself, had never set foot inside
a house of this kind in my life.
我对接下来会发生什么知之甚少。
I understood very little about
the events that were to follow.
但最后，我意识到，
But, eventually,
I came to recognize,
当一大笔财产的去处悬而未决，
when the destiny of a great fortune
is at stake,
人类的贪婪，和血管里的毒药，扩散得一样快。
men's greed spreads like a poison
in the bloodstream.
叔叔，侄子，表亲，
Uncles, nephews, cousins,
夫家的远房姻亲。
in-laws of increasingly
tenuous connection.
老妇亲缘关系最远的亲戚，
The old woman's most
distant relations
都来分这大房子的一杯羹。
had come foraging out
of the woodwork.
在这集会的最前头，有个令人困惑的巧合，
At the head of this congregation,
it was a disorienting coincidence,
我们发现了饭店的卡瓦斯副手，
we discovered our own Deputy Kovacs,
当然，他也是位名律师。
himself an important
attorney, of course.
他来执行这位去世寡妇的遗产。
He was the executor
of the dead widow's estate.
这是D夫人的遗愿和遗嘱。
This is Madame D's last
will and testament.
其中包括，
It consists of a general tontine
46年前，她丈夫去世前签署的一份养老保险，
drawn up before the event of her
husband's death 46 years ago,
以及635条改动，
in combination with 635 amendments,
标记，修正和遗书，
notations, corrections,
and letters of wishes
这些要在接下来的数十年间执行。
executed during the
subsequent decades.
这堆东西的最终合法权
The ultimate legality
of this accumulation
需要进一步证实，
requires further analysis,
但本办公室认为，D夫人的意愿是，
but in the opinion of this office,
it was Madame D's intention
将她的大批财产，
that control of the
vast bulk of her estate
立即移交至她儿子迪米崔名下，
should be transferred, forthwith,
to her son, Dmitri,
并为她的姐妹准备了特殊补贴，
with special allowances
for his sisters,
她们是玛格丽特，拉提莎和卡洛琳娜，
Marguerite, Laetizia, and Carolina,
还为家族内其余各位准备了小礼物，
and minor gifts for various members
of the extended family
领受人名单在此，我会在适当时候阐明。
as shown in the List of Recipients,
which I will elucidate in due course.
然而，
However.
有一条遗嘱附录，
An additional codicil,
刚刚在今早被邮送到我手上，
delivered into my possession
by post only this morning,
而且所有证据表明，这是出自D夫人之手，
and, by all indications,
sent by Madame D
是她在生命中最后几小时写下，
during the last hours of her life,
内容是对原证明的一条改动，
contains an amendment
to the original certificate,
由于法律规定，我现在将念给你们听。
which, as prescribed by law,
I will read to you now.
这份文件的真实性，
The authenticity of this document
还没有被主审裁判官证实，
has not yet been confirmed
by the presiding magistrate,
所以我请求所有人员耐心聆听，不予置评，
so I ask that all parties be patient
and refrain from comment
直至我们完成调查。
until such time as our
investigations can be completed.
"至我敬爱的，在我晚年安抚我的朋友，
"To my esteemed friend
who comforted me in my later years
"你为一位老女人的生活带来了阳光，
"and brought sunshine
into the life of an old woman
"她曾以为此生不会再快乐。
"who thought
that she would never be happy again.
古斯塔夫.H先生，
"Monsieur Gustave H,
"在免除一切税务的情况下，以我完全绝对的受托人权力，我遗赠、授予并转送你，
"I bequeath, bestow and devise,
free of all taxation
"我遗赠、授予并转送你，
"and with full and absolute
fiduciary entitlement,
"'拿苹果的男孩'这幅画...
"the painting known as
'Boy with Apple...'"
- 哇！
- "...由翰纳斯.范.霍特..."
- Wow!
- "...by Johannes van Hoytl..."
- 难以置信。
- "...二世所作..."
- I can't believe it.
- "...the younger..."
- 什么？
- "它为我们带来了如此多的欢乐。"
- What?
- "which gave us both so much pleasure."
范.霍特？
The van Hoytl?
- 免税？
- 她能这么做吗？
- Tax-free?
- Can she do that?
谁是古斯塔夫.H？
Who's Gustave H?
亲爱的，恐怕那个人是我。
I'm afraid that's me, darling.
你个死基佬！
That fucking faggot!
他是个门房！你来这干什么？
He's a concierge. What
are you doing here?
我来此为我爱过的伟大女人致敬。
I've come to pay my respects
to a great woman whom I loved.
- 这人入侵了我家！
- 这还不是你家呢，迪米崔。
- This man is an intruder in my home!
- It's not yours yet, Dmitri.
只有当遗嘱经过检验，而且权利契约...
Only when probate is granted,
and the Deed of Entitlement...
你不能拿走拿着苹果的男孩，你这个该死的小基佬！
You're not getting Boy with Apple,
you goddamn little fruit!
这话应该让我有什么感觉？
How's that supposed to make me feel?
叫警察来。我们要告你。
Call the police.
We're pressing charges.
这个罪犯毒害我的家庭将近20年。
This criminal has plagued my family
for nearly 20 years.
他是个无情的投机者，还是个假艺术家，
He's a ruthless adventurer
and a con-artist
专挑精神空虚，身体衰弱的老妇人下手，
who preys on mentally feeble,
sick old ladies,
说不定还上她们呢！
and he probably fucks them, too!
我和我所有的朋友都睡过。
I go to bed with all my friends.
赛琳在哪儿？
Where's Celine?
什么？她死了。咱们在听她的遗嘱呢。
What? She's dead.
We're reading her will.
哦是啊，是啊，当然是了。
Oh, yes, yes, of course.
要是让我知道，你曾经碰过我母亲的身体，
If I learn you ever once
laid a finger on my mother's body,
不管是在她活着的时候还是死了之后，我发誓！
我要割了你的脖子！听见了吗？
living or dead, I swear to God,
I'll cut your throat! You hear me?
我以为我是个该死的基佬呢。
I thought I was supposed to be
a fucking faggot.
- 你是，但你是双性恋。
- 咱们换个话题吧。
- You are, but you're bisexual.
- Let's change the subject.
我要走了。
I'm leaving.
那张画，拿着苹果的男孩，是无价之宝。明白吗？
That picture, Boy with Apple,
is priceless. Understand?
恭喜你，古斯塔夫先生！
Congratulations, Monsieur Gustave!
他们要为了这个小混蛋和我打架。
They're going to fight me
for the son of a bitch.
- 它美吗？
- 难以言喻。
- Is it very beautiful?
- Beyond description.
"骚客之诗，意蕴无穷，
"E'en the most gifted bard's rhyme
can only sing
"然难言其妙！
"but to the lack of her
and all she isn't!
-"其舌..."
- 我能看看吗？
- "His tongue doth..."
- Can I see it?
为什么不呢。
I don't see why not.
这是范.霍特最为精致的肖像
This is van Hoytl's
exquisite portrayal
画了一位束发之年的漂亮男孩。
of a beautiful boy on
the cusp of manhood.
金发。光滑。皮肤和那杯牛奶一样雪白。
Blond, smooth.
Skin as white as that milk.
无暇。
Of impeccable provenance.
最后留在民间的珍品中，这无疑是最好的。
One of the last in private hands,
and unquestionably, the best.
杰作。
It's a masterpiece.
其他的都是没用的垃圾。
The rest of this shit
is worthless junk.
我能帮你点什么？
有的，瑟奇。
请帮我把它包起来。
把“拿着苹果的男孩”包起来...?
你之前想和我说什么？
What did you want
to tell me, before?
我想我没法现在说。
I think I cannot say right now.
明天给我写信吧。去路兹巴汉车站！
Write me tomorrow. Lutzbahn Station!
我不想与它分离。
I'll never part with it.
这让她想起我，也会让我想起她。永远。
It reminded her of me.
It will remind me of her. Always.
我死的时候要把它挂在床头。
I'll die with this
picture above my bed.
看我们像不像？
See the resemblance?
嗯，像。
Oh, yes.
事实上我们应该把它卖了。
Actually, we should sell it.
赶早不赶晚，以防他们想把画偷回去。
Sooner rather than later,
in case they try to steal it back.
而且，列车上那些疯颠颠的步兵...
Plus, something about those lunatic
foot-soldiers on the express...
这可能是咱们饭店行业的一场棘手战斗，也会迎来很长的萧条期。
This could be a tricky war and a
long dry spell in the hotel trade.
据我所知，他们在明天就能追上咱们。
For all we know, they could
board us up tomorrow.
咱们做个庄严的血誓吧。
Let's make a solemn blood-pact.
咱们联系黑市，在这周末把拿着苹果的男孩
We'll contact the black market
and liquidate Boy with Apple
兑成现款，
by the end of the week,
然后离开这个国家，在马耳他海滨沿岸的某处低调生活
then leave the country and lay low
somewhere along the Maltese Riviera
直到风波平息，咱们再回到岗位上。
until the troubles blow over
and we resume our posts.
作为你提供帮助，对我忠诚，
In exchange for your
help, your loyalty
并作为我私人男仆的交换，
and your services as
my personal valet,
我保证给你净销售价的1.5%。
I pledge to you 1.5%
of the net sale price.
- 1.5？
- 包住宿和路费。
- 1.5?
- Plus room and board.
- 能给我10个百分点吗？
- 10？你开玩笑呢？
- Could we make it 10?
- 10? Are you joking?
那比我给画贩子的都多，
That's more than I'd
pay an actual dealer,
而且光啃鸡杂碎你又不会懂明暗对照法。
and you wouldn't know
chiaroscuro from chicken giblets.
不行，1.5正好。但是我告诉你，
No, 1.5 is correct. But
I'll tell you what,
如果我先死了，我肯定会让你成为我的唯一继承人。
if I die first, and I most certainly
will, you will be my sole heir.
咱们的资产不多只有一套象牙背面的梳子
There's not much in the kitty except
a set of ivory-backed hairbrushes
和我收藏的浪漫诗集，
and my library of romantic poetry,
但到时候，这些都是你的，
but when the time comes,
these will be yours,
还有咱们没花在找姑娘和喝酒上的所有玩意。
along with whatever we haven't
already spent on whores and whiskey.
咱们神圣地结盟。
This is our sacred bond.
我得现在写下来。
I'll draw it up right now.
我，古斯塔夫.H先生，目前精神和身体状况尚算完好，
I, Monsieur Gustave H, being of
relatively sound mind and body,
在今天，十月19日，于我主的1932年...
on this day, the 19th of October,
in the year of our Lord 1932...
他从没告诉我他从哪里来。
He never told me where he came from.
我也从未问过他家人是谁。
I never asked who his
family had been.
打扰一下。
Excuse me.
嗯哼？
Uh-huh?
警察来了，要见你。
The police are here.
They asked for you.
告诉他们我马上就来。
Tell them I'll be right down.
好。
Okay.
你被当局审问过吗？
Have you ever been questioned
by the authorities?
有过，有一次我被叛军抓走折磨
Yes, on one occasion I was arrested
and tortured by the rebel militia
就在沙漠起义之后。
after the Desert Uprising.
- 那你就知道该怎么办了。别说话。
- 没问题。
- You know the drill, then. Zip it.
- Of course.
你这辈子没听过“范.霍特”这个词。好，我们走。
You've never heard the word "van
Hoytl" in your life. Okay, let's go.
我们可以为你做点什么，先生们？
How may we serve you, gentlemen?
啊，是汉克斯督查。
Ah, Inspector Henckels.
"根据朱波罗卡省警务处处长的命令，
"By order of the Commissioner
of Police, Zubrowka Province,
"我在此将你拘留，
"I hereby place you under arrest
for the murder
"罪名是谋杀塞琳.维伦纽.戴斯高夫塔克西斯。"
"of Madame Ceine Villeneuve
Desgoffe und Taxis."
我就知道有什么不对劲。我们并不知道死因。
I knew there was something fishy.
We never got the cause of death.
她被杀了，你认为是我做的。
She's been murdered and
you think I did it.
嘿！
Hey!
站住！
Stop!
发生了什么？
What happened?
发生了什么，亲爱的零，就是我打得那个小矮子，
What happened, my dear Zero,
is I beat the living shit
小粉.班迪斯基涕泗横流，
out of a sniveling little runt
called Pinky Bandinski
他有胆子质疑我的男子气概，
who had the gall to
question my virility,
如果我们能从这场廉价的闹剧中学到点什么，
because if there's one thing we've
learned from penny dreadfuls,
那就是，当你发现身处于这样的地方时，
it's that, when you find yourself
in a place like this,
可千万别当软蛋。
you must never be a candy-ass.
你得从第一天就证明自己。
You've got to prove
yourself from Day One.
你得赢得他们的尊重。
You've got to win their respect.
你应该好好看看他早上那张丑脸。
You should take a long look
at his ugly mug this morning.
他，其实，变成了我的好朋友。
He's, actually,
become a dear friend.
我希望以后你能见见他。
You'll meet him, I hope.
那么，你和卡瓦斯谈过了吗？
So. You've talked to Kovacs?
我昨晚偷偷见他了。
I saw him last night in secret.
他让我用圣经起誓不会告诉别人。
He made me take an oath on a
Bible I wouldn't tell a soul.
- 你也应该这样做。
- 一会儿吧。
- You're supposed to also.
- I'll do that later.
- 他怀疑你是无辜的。
- 他当然要怀疑了。
- He suspects you're innocent.
- Of course he does.
罪名是什么？
What's the charge?
十月19日凌晨，
In the small hours
of the evening of 19 October,
这里大大小小都认识的人，古斯塔夫先生，
an individual well-known to the house
and staff, a Monsieur Gustave H,
来到了路兹的戴斯高夫塔克西斯宅邸，
did arrive at the Desgoffe
und Taxis residence in Lutz
从后巷进入，
and entered by the
rear service alley,
没让任何人发现他的到来，
alerting no one to his presence,
而后从走过后楼梯和仆人通道，
and did then proceed by way of
back stairs and servants' passage,
来到D夫人的私室。
to deliver himself into
the private chambers of Madame D.
没有证据表明这次来访
There is no evidence
to indicate whether this visit
是否有与她事先安排。
had been pre-arranged
with her or not.
第二天D夫人被发现死于宁碱中度。
The next morning Madame D was
found dead by strychnine poisoning.
古斯塔夫先生没再出现在此房内，
Monsieur Gustave was not observed
on the premises again
当然，直到24小时后。
until, of course, 24 hours later.
原告的身份已在证言中表明。
The identity of his accusers is made
clear in this notarized deposition.
他们主要包括，家族内所有成员，
They include, essentially,
all members of the extended family,
但宣称见证以上事件的关键目击证人，
but the key witness who actually
ostensibly saw the alleged events
逃离了司法管辖。
appears to have fled
the jurisdiction.
目前他行踪不明，
His whereabouts are
currently unknown,
但相关当局正在搜捕他。
but he's being sought and pursued
by the relevant authorities.
他是谁？
Who is he?
- 瑟奇？
- 恐怕是的。
- Serge?
- I'm afraid so.
那个小杂种。
That little prick.
不我不相信。他们陷害他的。
No, I don't believe it.
They put him up to it.
我算是掉进蛇窝了。
I've been dropped into
a nest of vipers.
你能辩解吗？
You have an alibi?
当然，但她嫁给了威斯特法拉公爵。
Of course, but she's married
to the Duke of Westphalia.
我不能让她的姓氏被这样胡闹。
I can't allow her name to get
mixed-up in all this monkey business.
- 你危在旦夕啊。
- 我知道，但这混蛋跑了。
- Your life may be at stake.
- I know, but the bitch legged it.
她已经登上了皇后纳斯塔莎号，快到荷属坦噶尼喀了。
She's already onboard the Queen
Nasstasja halfway to Dutch Tanganyika.
别放弃。
Don't give up.
这场合谋的细节，
The details of the conspiracy,
现在有案可查，
now a matter of public record,
而当时，我们无法获得。
were, at that time,
impossible for us to apprehend.
我在找瑟奇.X，
I'm looking for Serge X,
一个为我雇主服务的年轻人，
a young man in the
service of my employer,
在路兹城的戴斯高夫塔克西斯家里工作。
the family Desgoffe und Taxis
of Schloss Lutz.
- 怎么了，先生？
- 你是他的姐姐？
- Yes, sir?
- You're his sister?
- 是的，先生。
- 最近见过他吗？
- Yes, sir.
- Seen him lately?
- 没有，先生。
- 没有，先生？
- No, sir.
- No, sir?
没有，先生。
No, sir.
我得立即找到他，为了保护他
I need to find him right away,
for his own safety
以及大家。
and everybody else's.
如果他出现...
If he shows up...
- 是的，先生？
- 告诉他杰普林说了，
- Yes, sir?
- Tell him Jopling says,
"回家吧。"
"Come home."
但有一件事很肯定，
But one thing was certain,
戴斯高夫塔克西斯家非常显赫，
the Desgoffe und Taxis
were a very powerful family,
而且我们没时间了。
and time was not on our side.
古斯塔夫先生的来信。
零。
A letter from Monsieur Gustave.
Zero.
- 你想让我读？
- 读吧。
- You want me to?
- Read it.
"我亲爱的，可信的同事们..."
"My dear and trusted colleagues..."
我深深地想念你们，因此我在这监禁我的，
I miss you deeply
as I write from the confines
可悲又荒谬的栏杆后面，给你们写信。
of my regrettable
and preposterous incarceration.
直到我再次恢复自由身，
Until I walk amongst you again
as a free man,
布达佩斯大饭店都在你们手中，
the Grand Budapest remains
in your hands,
而它完美的地位也在你们手中。
as does its impeccable reputation.
维护它的无瑕，光耀它，
Keep it spotless and glorify it.
对每一丁丁点小角落都爱护有加，
Take extra special care
of every little-bitty bit of it
好似我还在盯着你们，像只老鹰一样，
as if I were watching
over you like a hawk
爪子里还抓着马鞭。没错，我就是这样。
with a horse whip in its talons,
because I am.
如果我发现，我离开的时候有任何一丝改变，
Should I discover a lapse
of any variety during my absence,
我发誓，正义会立刻无情地制裁你。
I promise, swift and merciless
justice will descend upon you.
一座伟大又高贵的房子正要你们来守护。
A great and noble house has been
placed under your protection.
如有任何不规矩的事发生，告诉零。
Tell Zero if you see
any funny business.
"爱你们的，古斯塔夫先生。"
"Your devoted Monsieur Gustave."
这之后还有一首诗，但我们也许可以开始喝汤了，
Then there's a poem, but we
might want to start on the soup
因为这诗有46节长。
since it's 46 stanzas.
"一粒黑色、微潮的灰尘，沾湿了黑鼠窝的污秽
"A moist, black ash dampens the
filth of a dung-dark rat's nest
"又混杂了腐木浓厚的香气
"and mingles with the thick scent
of wood rot
"流浪儿像百灵鸟一样唱起歌..."
"while the lark song
of a guttersnipe..."
我从不相信那个管家。
I never trusted that butler.
- 他太诚实了。
- 你说他太诚实了？
- He's too honest.
- Too honest, you say?
好吧，那，如果可以的话，找到他，解决他。
Right, well, be that as it may,
find him quick and make it snappy.
犯人们，有要喝玉米粥的吗？
May I offer any of you inmates
a plate of mush?
没有吗？
No? Anyone?
那位脸上有一大块疤的呢？
You with the very large
scar on your face?
试试吧。今天早上它还是热乎的，又有营养。
Try it. It's actually quite warm
and nourishing this morning.
来一撮盐。
It needs a dash of salt.
日安。
Good day.
玉米粥，先生们，有人喝吗？
Mush, gents? Any takers?
请便。
Suit yourselves.
起床啦。快，快。
Rise and shine. Chop, chop.
早上好，小粉。
Good morning, Pinky.
- 又是门德尔家的点心？
- 正是。
- Mendl's again?
- Precisely.
谁有割喉刀？
Who's got the throat slitter?
- 无可比拟。
- 门德尔家是最棒的的。
- Out of this world.
- Mendl's is the best.
- 好了，该干活了。
- 古斯塔夫先生？
- Well, back to work.
- Monsieur Gustave?
嗯？
Yes?
我和伙计们谈了谈。
Me and the boys talked it over.
我们认为你真的很正直。
We think you're a
really straight fellow.
从来没人骂过我正直，
Well, I've never been accused
of that before,
不过我很欣赏你的观点。
but I appreciate the sentiment.
你是我们的一员了。
You're one of us now.
这话说得真好。
What a lovely thing to say.
谢谢，亲爱的小粉。
谢谢，顾瑟。
Thank you, dear Pinky.
Thank you, Günther.
谢谢，老狼。
Thank you, Wolf.
还有别的事儿吗？
Anything else?
路德维格，告诉他。
Tell him, Ludwig.
19号检查站并不是个好搞定的拘留所。
Checkpoint 19 ain't
no two-bit hoosegow.
他们在每扇门窗还有通风口上，都宽宏大量地安了铁栏杆。
You got broad-gauge iron bars
on every door, vent and window.
一层楼有72个守卫，塔里还有16个。
You got 72 guards on the floor
and 16 more in the towers.
护城河那有个325英尺的洞，河里全是鳄鱼。
You got a 325-foot drop
into a moat full of crocodiles.
但就和所有的好监狱一样，它也有弱点，
But, like the best of them,
it's got a soft spot,
在这儿恰巧就是
which in this case
happens to take the form
雨水下水道系统，
of a storm-drain sewer system
它的年头得追溯到中世纪
dating from the time
of the original rock fortification
还用石头筑垒的时候了。
way back in the Middle Ages.
现在，我不是说这是要在林荫大道，
Now, nobody's saying it's a stroll
down a tree-lined promenade
和一位漂亮小姐还有只白色贵宾散步，
with a fine lady and a white poodle,
但这就是你得称作“漏洞”的东西，
but it's got what you'd
call "vulnerability,"
这就是我们的命根了。
and that's our bread and butter.
看。
Take a look.
谁画的？
Who drew this?
你这话什么意思？我画的。
What do you mean,
"Who drew this?" I did.
画得好。你的线条画的太棒了，路德维格。
Very good. You've got a
wonderful line, Ludwig.
这是极大的艺术天赋。
This shows great artistic promise.
问题是，你打算怎么穿透这个又低又旧的下水道？
Question, how do you intend
to penetrate this lowest rudiment?
它是25英寸的花岗岩加固砌成的，不是吗？
It's 25 inches of reinforced
granite masonry, is it not?
拿一把割喉刀挖，
Digging with the throat-slitter,
我想至少要连续挖上3到6个月，
I expect this would take three
to six months of continual effort,
在此期间，我们中有数位，
during which time
several of our members
都要被残忍地处死。
will have been violently executed.
你说到点上了，古斯塔夫先生。
You hit the nail on the
head, Mr. Gustave.
我们有假证件，二手衣服，
We got fake documents,
second-hand street clothes,
一个用棍子和床铺线绳做的绳梯，
a rope ladder made of
sticks and bunk-linens,
但我们需要挖掘工具，
but we need digging tools,
在这破地方可不好拿。
which are proving hard to come by
in this flop-house.
故事讲到这里，
At this point in the story,
老人突然沉默，并把桌上的羊脊肉推开。
the old man fell silent
and pushed away his saddle of lamb.
他的双眼像石头一样没了光彩。
His eyes went blank as two stones.
看得出来，他陷入了痛苦。
I could see he was in distress.
- 你病了吗，穆斯塔法先生？
- 我终于问出了口。
- Are you ill, Mr. Moustafa?
- I finally asked.
- 哦老天，没有。
- 他说。
- Oh, dear me, no.
- He said.
我只是不知道该如何说下去。
It's only that I don't
know how to proceed.
他流泪了。
He was crying.
你瞧，我从没讲过阿加莎的事，
You see, I never speak of Agatha,
因为仅仅想起她的名字，
because even at the
thought of her name
我都没办法控制住情绪。
I'm unable to control my emotions.
好吧，我想也没别的办法了。
Well, I suppose there's
no way around it.
你看，是她救了我们。
You see, she saved us.
在我们第三次正式约会时，
On our third formal rendezvous,
我向她求婚，她答应了。
I had asked for her hand in marriage
and she had agreed.
- 嫁给我好吗？
- 好。
- Will you marry me?
- Yes.
我们两个人身上连50块钱都没有。
We did not have 50 Klubecks
between the two of us.
我俩当然并不知情，但知道了，谁又会在乎呢？
No one knew, of course,
but, then, who would have cared?
世界仿佛就剩下我们两个，
We were each
completely on our own in the world,
而我们如此相爱。
and we were deeply in love.
- 给你。
- 谢谢。
- Here.
- Thank you.
- 是本书。
- 这样。
- It's a book.
- I see.
浪漫诗选，第一卷。
Romantic Poetry, Volume One.
古斯塔夫先生推荐的，我自己也有一本。
Monsieur Gustave recommended it.
I have a copy of my own as well.
- 我想我把惊喜给破坏了。
- 我怎么都要打开的。
- I ruined the surprise, I suppose.
- I'll go ahead and open it, anyway.
读读献词。
Read the inscription.
古斯塔夫先生坚持，
Monsieur Gustave insisted
要对我立刻彻底的盘问...
on an immediate
and thorough cross-examination...
她真迷人。她太迷人了。
She's charming. She's so charming.
期间，他向阿加莎展示了一个瓷吊坠
during which he presented Agatha
with a porcelain pendant
还有五打自己包装的白郁金香，
and five dozen individually
tissue-wrapped white tulips
都放在一个婴儿棺材般大的盒子里。
in a box the size of
a child's coffin.
- 这样不对。
- 您说什么？
- It's not right.
- I beg your pardon?
他怎么气哼哼的？
Why is he sulking?
她是我女朋友。
你不能这么给她买东西。
She's my girlfriend.
You can't just buy her things.
我只是代表你，和这个孤独美丽的幻景说说话。
I'm only interviewing this vision
of loveliness on your behalf.
这辈子也别嫉妒别人，零，一秒钟也别嫉妒。
Never be jealous in this life, Zero,
not even for an instant.
他是不是在和你调情？
Is he flirting with you?
- 是的。
- 我同意你们结合。
- Yes.
- I approve of this union.
阿加莎，我的美人，回到你挚爱的人身旁吧。
Agatha, my beauty,
return to your beloved.
很快我们就知道...
Soon we learned...
祝福你们两个。
Blessings upon you both.
阿加莎不仅仅是非常精通
not only was Agatha
immensely skilled
使用铲刀和黄油奶油花式...
with a palette knife
and a butter-cream flourish...
- 门德尔来了。
- 快。
- Mendl.
- Go.
她还十分勇敢。
she was also very brave.
我想她生来就是那样。
I believe she was born that way.
少点什么。
Something's missing.
一份关键的文件，要么就是找不见了，
要么，可想而知，被毁了。
A crucial document, either misplaced
or, conceivably, destroyed.
我不知道上面写了什么，
我不知道那代表着什么，
I don't know what it contains,
I don't know what it represents,
我不知道那是什么，
I don't know what it is,
但是到处有都它的踪影。
but there are traces
and shadows of it everywhere.
我现在不是想警告你们，
Now, I don't want to alarm you,
而且我不希望，
and I don't expect to see any
significant change
裁判官对你财产继承的最终裁决有什么大的变动，
in the magistrate's ultimate decision
vis-a-vis your own inheritance,
但，尤其是鉴于她死亡的特殊情况，
but, especially given the
circumstances of the death,
以及谋杀案的关键证人，瑟奇.X消失不见，
as well as the disappearance of the key
witness in the murder case, Serge X,
我建议我们立刻把这件事
I suggest that
we immediately bring this matter
上报至市督查
to the attention of the
municipal inspector
这样才不会在未来
so that there can be
absolutely no question
有任何不得体的事情发生。
of impropriety at any future date.
- 同意吗？
- 不同意。
- Agreed?
- Not agreed.
- 不同意？
- 不同意。
- Not agreed?
- Not agreed.
- 我能问个问题吗，维莫斯？
- 请说，迪米崔？
- Can I ask you a question, Vilmos?
- Yes, Dmitri?
- 你究竟为谁工作？
- 您说什么？
- Who are you working for?
- I beg your pardon?
你为谁工作？我还以为你是我们的律师。
Who are you working for? I thought
you're supposed to be our lawyer.
唔，实际上，我是遗产执行人。
Well, in point of fact,
I'm the executor of the estate.
在这种特殊情况下，我代表去世的夫人。
In this particular situation,
I represent the deceased.
哦是吗？
Oh, yeah?
是的，付给我的款项里包括...
Yeah. A provision for my fees
was included in the...
别废话了，也别和我争，同意吗？
Just wrap it up
and don't make waves. Agreed?
我是名律师。我的义务是根据法律处理事情。
I'm an attorney. I'm obligated to
proceed according to the rule of law.
不同意。
Not agreed.
姐妹们，这可真讨厌。
This stinks, sisters.
他刚刚把我的猫扔到窗外了？
Did he just throw my
cat out the window?
我不这么认为。
I don't think so.
- 没有吧，扔了吗？
- 杰普林？
- No. Did he?
- Jopling?
好吧。
Okay.
有件事我没告诉你，阿加莎。
There's something
I haven't told you, Agatha.
- 说吧。
- 我们偷了一幅画。
- Okay.
- We stole a painting.
它非常值钱，可能值500万吧。
It's very valuable, maybe five
million Klubecks, in fact.
我不知道目前别人有没有注意到它丢了，
I don't know if anyone's
even noticed it's missing yet,
但如果我出了什么事...
but if something
should happen to me...
你偷了艺术品？
You steal art?
一张画。不管怎么说，为了让你活下去，
我们得做好计划。
One picture. Anyway, we need
to make a plan for your survival.
把这个藏起来。这个加密了，而且你得用放大镜读
Hide this. It's in code and you might
need a magnifying glass to read it,
但是它能告诉你拿着苹果的男孩在哪，怎么找。
but it tells you exactly where
and how to find Boy with Apple.
卖的时候不要少于半价。而且...
Don't take less than half
the retail asking price. Also...
- 零，我是个面包师。
- 你是个糕点大厨。
- Zero, I'm a baker.
- You're a pastry chef.
我不销赃，如果我没用错词的话。
I'm not a fence, if that's the term.
我不卖脏物。
I don't trade in stolen property.
我刚才说得不对。
画是她给他的。
I said it wrong.
She willed it to him.
睡吧。
Go to sleep.
是的，门德尔先生。
Yes, Herr Mendl.
- 藏好它。
- 不要。
- Hide this.
- No.
好吧，不管怎样，拿着吧。
Okay, but take it anyway.
隔天早上，先生收到了
The next morning,
Herr Becker received a peculiar,
卡瓦斯副手办公室的临时通知，
last-minute notice
from the office of Deputy Kovacs,
推后他们约好的会面，直至永远。
postponing their scheduled meeting,
in perpetuity.
走吧。
Let's blow.
- 你们怎么出来的？
- 快他妈闭嘴。
- How did you get out there?
- Shut the fuck up.
这些人要逃跑。
These guys are trying to escape.
你告发我们，有病吧？
What's wrong with you,
you goddamn snitch?
守卫！守卫！
Guard! Guard!
是你呀。谢谢。谢谢。贴心，善良的你。
It's you. Thank you.
Thank you, you sweet, kind man.
好。
Okay.
我猜这算得上平手。
I suppose you'd call that a draw.
晚上好。
Good evening.
让我介绍一下。小粉，老狼，路德维格，
这是伟大的零。
Let me introduce you. Pinky, Wolf,
Ludwig, this is the divine Zero.
顾瑟在地下墓穴被杀了。
Günther was slain in the catacombs.
好了，小伙子们，不知道我们什么时候能再见，
但如果有一天...
Well, boys, who knows when we'll
all meet again, but if one day...
等会。
Hold it.
没时间瞎扯了。
No time to gab.
保证，古斯塔夫先生。
Take care of yourself, Mr. Gustave.
祝你好运，孩子。
Good luck, kid.
- 那条路通往安全屋？
- 我没找到安全屋。
- Which way to the safe house?
- I couldn't find one.
没有安全屋？真没有？
我们现在就得靠自己？
No safe house? Really?
We're completely on our own out here?
恐怕是的。我四处问了，但...
I'm afraid so.
I asked around, but...
我理解。太冒险了。我们可以随机应变。
I understand. Too risky. We'll
just have to wing it, I suppose.
那咱们乔装一下吧。
Let's put on our disguises.
- 我们已经乔装了。
- 不我们没有。
- We're wearing them.
- No, we're not.
我们说好了有假胡子和假鼻子什么的。
We said false whiskers
and fake noses and so on.
- 你没带来？
- 我觉得你正在长胡子呢。
- You didn't bring any?
- I thought you were growing one.
那看起来更像真的，不是吗？
And it wouldn't look
realistic, would it?
是，如果弄得好，看起来就像是真的。
No, when done properly,
they're perfectly convincing.
不过我理解你的意思。就这样吧。
But I take your point. So be it.
给我喷几下华丽香氛古龙水，好吗？
Give me a few squirts of
L'air de Panache, please, will you?
- 我连香水都不能喷吗？
- 我把华丽香氛忘了。
- Can I not get a squirt, even?
- I forgot the L'air de Panache.
说真的，你没带华丽香氛？
Honestly, you forgot
the L'air de Panache?
难以置信。你怎么能这样？
I don't believe it. How could you?
我可是蹲了大牢，零！你不明白这有多屈辱吗？
I've been in jail, Zero! Do you
understand how humiliating this is?
我身上不好闻。
I smell.
这可真棒，是吧？
That's just marvelous, isn't it?
我想这要是在...你从哪儿来的来着？
I suppose this is to be expected back
in... Where do you come from again?
- 阿克萨利阿-扎巴。
- 对。
- Aq Salim al-Jabat.
- Precisely.
我想这要是在阿克萨利阿-扎巴才会这样，
I suppose this is to be expected
back in Aq Salim al-Jabat
每个人最珍贵的物件
where one's prized possessions
就是一捆脏毯子，还有一头快饿死的羊，
are a stack of filthy carpets
and a starving goat,
人都睡在帐篷里，得靠野枣和圣甲虫才能活。
and one sleeps behind a tent flap and
survives on wild dates and scarabs.
但这不是我教你的。
But it's not how I trained you.
究竟你是着了什么魔，
What on God's earth
possessed you to leave
才会离开你的家乡，而不呆在该呆的地方，
the homeland where
you obviously belong
走了不知多远，才能来这成为一名身无分文的移民。
and travel unspeakable distances
to become a penniless immigrant
这个高雅，有教养的社会，
in a refined,
highly-cultivated society
说实话，没你也一样运转得好好的？
that, quite frankly, could've
gotten along very well without you?
战争。
The war.
再说一次？
Say again?
唔，你看，我爸爸被杀害了，
Well, you see, my father was murdered
家里的其他人被射击队处死了。
and the rest of my family were
executed by firing squad.
我的村庄被烧毁，
Our village was burned to the ground
那些想办法活下来的人只能逃亡。
and those who managed to
survive were forced to flee.
我是因为战争才离开。
I left because of the war.
我明白了。所以你其实，某种程度上，
真的是个难民？
I see. So you're, actually, really
more of a refugee, in that sense?
没错。
Truly.
我想我最好收回刚才我说的一切。
Well, I suppose I'd better take
back everything I just said.
我真是个大傻瓜。
可悲的笨蛋。
What a bloody idiot I am.
Pathetic fool.
该死的自私鬼。
Goddamn, selfish bastard.
这太丢人了，而且远远低于布达佩斯大饭店的准则。
This is disgraceful, and it's beneath
the standards of the Grand Budapest.
我代表饭店向你道歉。
I apologize on behalf of the hotel.
这不是你的错。你只是因为我没带香水才沮丧的。
It's not your fault. You were
just upset I forgot the perfume.
别替我找借口。
我欠你一条命。
Don't make excuses for me.
I owe you my life.
你是我的好友，我的宠儿，我真为你骄傲。
You are my dear friend and protégé
and I'm very proud of you.
你一定要知道这点。
You must know that.
我很抱歉，零。
I'm so sorry, Zero.
咱们是兄弟。
We're brothers.
咱们亲爱的阿加莎怎么样？
How's our darling Agatha?
"初见她时，荒原上的第一束光，
"'Twas first light
when I saw her face upon the heath,
"让我折返，日复一日，如痴如醉，
"and hence did I return,
day-by-day, entranced,
"你的活力浸满我心，永不..."
"tho' vinegar did brine
my heart, never..."
很好。我得打断你，因为警报响了，
Very good. I'm going to stop you
there because the alarm has sounded,
但是记得我们逃走之后，一定要再说给我听。
but remember where we left off
because I insist you finish later.
我要在50公里内每个路口都设路障。
I want roadblocks
at every junction for 50km.
我要在100公里内每个火车站都设铁路检查。
I want rail blocks
at every train station for 100km.
五分钟内，我要50个人，10条猎犬做好准备。
I want 50 men and 10 bloodhounds
ready in five minutes.
我们要清查每个饼干屋，华夫饼小店，酒吧，
We're going to strip-search every
pretzel-Haus, Waffel-hut, Biergarten
尤其要查从奥根斯堡到兹克布洛克的每个大饭店。
and especially every grand hotel
from Augenzburg to Zilchbrock.
这些逃犯很危险，是专业的罪犯。
These men are dangerous,
professional criminals.
不管怎么说，至少他们中有三个是。
At least three of them are anyway.
你是谁？
Who are you?
你在这干嘛？平民不允许进入监狱区。
What are you doing here? Civilian personnel
aren't permitted in the cellblock.
- 这是军事调查。
- 这是杰普林先生，头儿。
- This is a military investigation.
- This is Mr. Jopling, sir.
他雇主的母亲是是受害者之一...
His employer's mother
was one of the victims...
闭嘴。
Shut up.
你为戴斯高夫塔克西斯家族工作？
You work for the family
Desgoffe und Taxis?
你知道十月23日维莫斯.卡瓦斯被杀了吗？
Are you aware of the murder of Deputy
Vilmos Kovacs on 23rd October?
我知道他消失了。
I'm aware of his disappearance.
他的尸体在昨晚找到的，被塞在昆斯艺术馆
His body was found stuffed in
a sarcophagus behind a storage room
储藏室的石棺内。
at the Kunstmuseum late last night.
他少了四只手指。
He was short four fingers.
- 你知道点什么嘛？
- 不知道。
- What do you know about that?
- Nothing.
送杰普林先生出去。
Escort Mr. Jopling off the premises.
门德尔家的。
Mendl's.
接线员，请替我接巴登-约根的精益宫，
Operator, get me the Excelsior
Palace in Baden-Jurgen
对方付费。
and reverse the charges, please.
我们没得选了。
没有别人可以求。
We've no choice.
There's nowhere else to turn.
好，我等着。谢谢。
I'll hold. Thank you.
这是我们唯一的希望了。否则，
我都不会向你提及它的存在。
It's our only hope. Otherwise, I shouldn't
even mention its existence to you.
不用说，别向任何一个生灵提起一个字。
It goes without saying, never breathe
a word about this to a living soul.
- 你发誓？
- 我发誓。不过是什么啊？
- Do you swear?
- Of course. What is it, in fact?
我不能告诉你。
I can't say.
一个人是怎样，只花了一天，
How does one come by
front-row aisle seats
就得到托斯塔纳剧院演出
第一晚第一排的通道座位？
for a first night at the Opera
Toscana with one day's notice?
第一个人是怎样安排了皇家萨克森画廊
How does one arrange
a private viewing
挂毯展的私人参观？
of the tapestry collection
at the Royal Saxon Gallery?
一个人是怎样留住星期四
How does one secure a corner table
多明尼克的角桌位置？
at Chez Dominique on a Thursday?
艾文，亲爱的，是我古斯塔夫。你好。
Ivan, darling, it's Gustave. Hello.
直到5分钟前还是那样的。
Well, I was until about
five minutes ago.
如果你能明白的话，我们刚才离开得挺匆忙的。
We've taken it upon ourselves to clear
out in a hurry if you see what I mean.
唔，碰巧是通过下水道离开的。对的。
Well, through a sewer,
as it happens. Exactly.
听着，艾文，我很抱歉打断你，但我们现在有困难。
Listen, Ivan, I'm sorry to cut you
off, but we're in a bit of a bind.
我正式请求保住。
This is an official request.
我代表特殊服务处，正式与你通话...
I'm formally calling
upon the special services of...
一会儿打给你，古斯塔夫。
I'll call you back, Gustave.
对，等着。
Right. Stand by.
不好意思。
您愿意走过去吗？
I beg your pardon.
Do you prefer to walk?
咱们就在这。很简单。
We're right here. It's very simple.
顺着滨海路直走，然后左转。
Straight down the
corniche, then left.
乔乔，陪这位先生出去。
Jojo, see the gentleman out.
请替我接通奢华堡的乔治先生。
Get me Monsieur Georges
at the Ch?teau Luxe, please.
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you
你来。
Take over.
生日快乐，亲爱的...
Happy birthday, dear...
喂，艾文？
Hello, Ivan?
了解。
Got it.
请替我接通公主殿的迪诺先生。
Get me Monsieur Dino
at the Palazzo Principessa, please.
再高点，该死的，高点！
Higher, goddammit, higher!
你来。
Take over.
- 乔治先生。
- 高点。
- Monsieur Georges.
- Higher.
了解了。这就办。
I see. Straightaway.
请替我接通开普岸饭店的罗宾先生。
Get me Monsieur Robin
at l'Hotel Cote du Cap, please.
二，三。
and two and three.
罗宾先生。迪诺先生来了电话。
Monsieur Robin. There's a call
from Monsieur Dino for you.
你来。
Take over.
- 一，二，三。
- 是的，迪诺。
- One, two, three.
- Yes, Dino.
是的，迪诺。好的，迪诺。
Yes, Dino. Okay, Dino.
请替我接通里兹皇家饭店的马丁先生。
Get me Monsieur Martin
at the Ritz Imperial, please.
盐太多。
Too much salt.
胡椒不够。
Not enough pepper.
你来。
Take over.
- 罗宾？我是马丁。
- 盐太多。
- Robin? Martin.
- Too much salt.
我听说了。
So I've heard.
也许吧。让我打几个电话。
Maybe. Let me make a few calls.
瑟奇.X，失踪。
卡瓦斯副手，也是失踪。
Serge X, missing.
Deputy Kovacs, also missing.
D夫人，死亡。
拿着苹果的的男孩，被窃，被咱俩。
Madame D, dead.
Boy with Apple, stolen, by us.
迪米崔和杰普林，无情，冷血，野蛮人。
Dmitri and Jopling, ruthless,
cold-blooded savages.
古斯塔夫.H，在逃。还有呢？
Gustave H, at large. What else?
- 零，困惑。
- 零，困惑，没错。
- Zero, confused.
- Zero, confused, indeed.
剧情"变浓重"了，正如他们所说。
The plot "thickens," as they say.
话说为什么呢？
为什么要用形容汤的词呢？
Why, by the way?
Is it a soup metaphor?
我不知道。
I don't know.
进来。
Get in.
我们找到了管家。
We found the butler.
他在嘉宝美斯特峰附近遥远的小山丘里躲着呢。
He's hiding out in the remote
foothills near Gabelmeister's Peak.
我们的联络人说服他与你在明天中午见面。
Our contact convinced him
to meet you midday tomorrow
在封顶的天文台。
at the observatory on the summit.
别告诉别人。
他会解释一切的。
Tell no one.
He'll explain everything.
你们的火车在四分半中内开动。
Your train departs
in four and a half minutes.
这是车票。
Here's your tickets.
- 三等舱？
- 票订没了。
- Third class?
- It was overbooked
但是售票员在老凡尔赛做过酒侍。
but the conductor used to be
a sommelier at the old Versailles.
他在背后帮了忙。
He pulled some strings.
你在餐车用得上这个。
You'll need these
for the dining car.
最后一件事。
One last thing.
华丽香氛。
L'air de Panache.
他们只剩半盎司了。
They only had the half-ounce.
我们至少得和他做做样子。
We should give him something
as a symbolic gesture.
- 你有多少钱？
- 42块钱和三张邮票。
- How much money you got?
- 42 Klubecks and 3 postage stamps.
给我25块。对。
Give me 25. Yes.
- 祝福你。
- 省省吧。
- Bless you.
- Please.
- 我得亲手给他。
- 天啊。
- I've got to hand it to him.
- Jesus Christ.
我没想到。
接下来你想怎么做？
I didn't see that coming.
Well, what do you want next?
和跛脚姑娘再聊一次，这次，要说服她们。
Talk to the club-footed sister again,
and, this time, be persuasive.
该死的混蛋！
Goddamn son of a bitch.
妈的！
Holy fuck!
这什么玩意？
What's the meaning of this shit?
拿着苹果的少年？我以为你藏起来了。
Boy with Apple? I thought
you'd hidden it.
- 你怎么现在才提？
- 我以为查税人拿走了。
- Why are you only noticing now?
- I assumed it went to the tax appraiser.
你他妈在逗我？
Are you fucking kidding me?
我想是被古斯塔夫先生拿走了。
I believe it was removed
by Monsieur Gustave.
我不生瑟奇的气。
I'm not angry with Serge.
你不能因为别人没有基本的道德品质
就责怪他们。
You can't blame someone
for their basic lack of moral fiber.
他是个惊慌，矮小，胆怯的懦夫。
He's a frightened, little,
yellow-bellied coward.
- 这不是他的错，对吧？
- 我不知道。要看情况。
- It's not his fault, is it?
- I don't know. It depends.
唔，对什么事你都可以这么说。
Well, you can say that
about most anything.
"看情况。"当然要看情况。
"It depends." Of course it depends.
当然要看情况。
Of course it depends.
我觉得你说的没错。
当然要看情况。
Yes, I suppose you're right.
Of course it depends.
这不代表我不会掐死那个小叛徒。
That doesn't mean I'm not going
to throttle the little swamp rat.
顺便一提，我可以主持婚礼吗？
May I officiate, by the way?
The ceremony?
荣幸之至。
With pleasure.
不得不说，那个姑娘真是让人快乐。
I must say, I find that
girl utterly delightful.
身子像块平板，半张脸上
Flat as a board, enormous birthmark
有着墨西哥形状的巨大胎记，
the shape of Mexico
over half her face,
连续几小时站在闷热的厨房里流汗，
sweating for hours on end
in that sweltering kitchen
而门德尔，真是个天才，
while Mendl, genius though he is,
像只大猩猩似的，傲视她。
looms over her like
a hulking gorilla.
但毫无疑问，毋庸置疑，
Yet without question, without fail,
一直不变的是，她太可爱了。
always and invariably,
she's exceedingly lovely.
为什么？
Why?
因为她纯真。
Because of her purity.
她也仰慕你，古斯塔夫先生。
She admires you as well,
Monsieur Gustave.
- 是吗？
- 是的，非常仰慕。
- Does she?
- Very much.
这挺好的，你懂。
这说明她能“明白到点上”。
That's a good sign, you know.
It means she "gets it."
这很重要。
That's important.
不许和她调情。
Don't flirt with her.
今早四点，一封电报由一位女孩签名寄出，
A radio telegram was delivered and
signed for by the girl at 4:00 AM.
信封在她尸体附近找到了，但是信不见了。
The envelope was found near the body,
but its contents were missing.
但是，电报局总是保留着24小时内自动收报机纸条的副本。
However, the telegraph office always keeps
a carbon of the ticker tape for 24 hours.
我抄了下来。
内容如下，
I copied it down.
It reads as follows,
"收拾好行李句号。
"Pack your things stop.
"立刻准备离开句号。
"Be ready to leave
at moment's notice stop.
"藏身地在嘉宝美斯特峰附近句号。
"Hide-out is vicinity
of Gabelmeister's Peak stop.
"删除这条信息，我爱你句号。"
"Destroy this message
all my love full stop."
篮子在哪儿？
Where's the basket?
先生，你要去哪儿？
Where you headed, mister?
滑雪？滑雪橇？爬山？
Skiing? Sledding? Mountain climbing?
三块钱。
Three Klubecks.
通过无线电，我给阿加莎写信，
By express wireless, I wrote Agatha
指示她前往我们预先安排好的藏身处，
with instructions to move
to our pre-arranged hideout,
就在那不勒堡路外头的吉卜赛拖车里，
a Gypsy caravan
on the outer Nebelsbad road,
而我和古斯塔夫先生一路朝东，
while Monsieur Gustave
and I continued east
直至朱波罗卡山，
into the Zubrowkian Alps,
向着与瑟奇.X管家的高纬度密会而去。
toward our high-altitude rendezvous
with the butler Serge X.
为防止被抓，我们悄悄地，
As a precaution, we
disembarked quietly
在车站外的货场下了车。
in the freight yard just
outside the station.
华丽香氛。
L'air de Panache.
这景色真好。它配得上这种夸奖。
It's a hell of a view. I give
them that, for what's it's worth.
我同意。
I agree.
"一如既往地，没有哪片落下的雪花，
"'Tis oft'-remarked, no single,
falling-flake does any other
- "和其他任何一片，有着相同纯洁又完美的形状..."
- 有人来了。
- "in its pure and perfect form..."
- Somebody's coming.
你是那不勒堡布达佩斯大饭店的古斯塔夫先生吗？
Are you Monsieur Gustave
of the Grand Budapest Hotel in Nebelsbad?
- 嗯哼。
- 上下一班缆车。
- Uh-huh.
- Get on the next cable car.
你是那不勒堡布达佩斯大饭店的古斯塔夫先生吗？
Are you Monsieur Gustave of the
Grand Budapest Hotel in Nebelsbad?
- 嗯哼。
- 和我换位置。
- Uh-huh.
- Switch with me.
你是那不勒堡布达佩斯大饭店的古斯塔夫先生吗？
Are you Monsieur Gustave of the
Grand Budapest Hotel in Nebelsbad?
- 嗯哼。
- 穿上，唱诗。
- Uh-huh.
- Put these on and sing.
- 你是那不勒堡的...
- 对，该死的。
- Are you Monsieur Gustave of the...
- Yes, dammit.
去忏悔。
Confess.
我是无罪的。
I'm innocent.
嗯？不对不对。
Hmm? No, no.
原谅我，古斯塔夫先生，我并没想背叛你。
Forgive me, Monsieur Gustave.
I never meant to betray you.
他们威胁要杀我，现在，他们杀死了我唯一的亲人。
They threatened my life and now
they've murdered my only family.
不是吧。他们这次杀了谁？
No. Who did they kill this time?
- 我亲爱的姐姐。
- 那个跛脚姑娘？
- My dear sister.
- The girl with the club foot?
- 对。
- 那些混蛋！
- Yes.
- Those fuckers!
我一开始想警告你的。
I tried to warn you
at the beginning.
亲爱的，我知道。过去的就过去了吧。
I know, darling. Let's
put that behind us.
听着，我很难受让你变成这样，
但我请求你为我正名。
Listen, I hate to put you on the spot, but
I really must ask you to clear my name.
- 很显然你还沉浸在悲痛中...
- 还没结束。
- Obviously you're grieving...
- There's more.
- 那个故事。
- 明白。你继续。
- To the story.
- I get it. Go on.
我是D夫人的官方证人，
I was the official witness
in Madame D's presence
见证她撰写第二份遗嘱，
to the creation of a second will
这份遗嘱只能在她被谋杀的情况下执行。
to be executed only in the event
of her death by murder.
- 第二份遗嘱？
- 对。
- A second will?
- Right.
- 以防她被做掉？
- 对。
- In case she got bumped off?
- Right.
- 嗯哼？
- 但是他们把遗嘱毁了。
- Uh-huh?
- But they destroyed it.
- 哦天哪。
- 然而...
- Oh, dear.
- However...
- 嗯哼？
- 我留了备份。
- Uh-huh?
- I pulled a copy.
第二份遗嘱的第二份备份？
A second copy of the second will?
- 对。
- 嗯哼？
- Right.
- Uh-huh?
上面写了什么？在哪儿呢？
该死的，究竟是什么内容？
What does it say? Where is it?
What's it all about, dammit?
别卖关子了。这他妈完全成了个噩梦。
Don't keep us in suspense. This has
been a complete fucking nightmare.
快他妈告诉我怎么了！
Just tell us what the
fuck is going on!
瑟奇？瑟奇？瑟奇！
Serge? Serge? Serge!
该死的。
他们把这个倒霉蛋勒死了。
Bloody hell.
They've strangled the poor slob.
来吧！我们走！
Come on! Let's go!
- 如果抓到他，我们该怎么办？
- 我不知道。
- What do we do if we catch him?
- I don't know.
他是个杀人狂魔。咱们别追了。
He's a homicidal psychopath.
Let's stop.
我停不下来。我快掌不住舵了。
I can't. I can barely steer.
你这个恶心，可悲的讨厌鬼。
我恨死你了。
You sick, pathetic creep.
I hate you.
"'如果这就是我的结局，那，永别了！'
负伤的风笛少年喊道，
"'If this do be me end, farewell!'
cried the wounded piper-boy,
"当火枪爆破，义勇军狂啸，
"whilst the muskets cracked
and the yeomen roared 'Hurrah!'
"土墙皆倒，
"And the ramparts fell.
"'我想我最后嗅到的，是我的恐惧'
他说道..."
"'Methinks me breathes me last,
me fears!' said he..."
天啊！你成功了！
Holy shit! You got him!
干得好！零！
Well done, Zero!
古斯塔夫H！你是脱离了制裁的逃犯！
Gustave H! You are a
fugitive from justice!
合法投降吧，我会亲自担保你
Surrender lawfully
and I will personally vouchsafe
收到公平审判。
your fair treatment.
不要尝试逃跑！
Do not attempt to flee!
- 你怎么想？
- 我不知道。
- What do you think?
- I don't know.
我宁愿现在从悬崖跳下去，也不回那个破监狱了。
I'd rather jump off this cliff right now
than go back to fucking prison.
我的看法是，咱们偷走那个死疯子的摩托车，
接上阿加莎，
I say we steal that sick maniac's
motorcycle, go fetch Agatha,
取回拿着苹果的男孩，，朝着马耳他海滨跑，
一劳永逸。
take back Boy with Apple and head for
the Maltese Riviera, once and for all.
很好！你太棒了，零。
谢谢。
Very good! You're so extraordinary, Zero.
Thank you.
让我们为那位在执行公务时，
A moment of silence
in memoriam of a devoted servant
被残忍杀害的忠仆，默哀一分钟。
killed violently
during the conduct of his duties.
再见了，瑟奇。
Goodbye, Serge.
好，我们出发。
Okay, let's go.
战争在午夜打响了。
The war began at midnight.
派弗斯塔德于午间，在密集炮击下沦陷，
Pffeifelstad fell by lunch
under heavy shelling,
有十个营沿西岸涌入。
and 10 battalions surged across
the long western border.
高官前进至那不勒堡。
High-command advanced to Nebelsbad.
门德尔先生，向行政层道贺。
Compliments of Herr Mendl,
for the executive staff.
斯蒂格兹将军要求住在有额外折叠床的
花园景致客厅房。
General Stieglitz requests a garden-view
sitting room with an extra roll-away.
让他住在赖博德公爵套间吧。
Let's put him in the
Duke Leopold Suite.
沃伦尼基秘书办公室来电。
Secretary Woroniecki's
office cabled.
他今天早些时候入住的。
401-2-3房。
He's checking in a day early.
Rooms 401-2-3.
告诉战略后勤部我们要把他们
Tell Tactical Logistics
we're moving them
挪到三楼的标准双人间内。
to a standard double
on the third floor.
他们需要更大的空间。
They'll need more space than that.
结尾的开始，和开始的结尾，都拉开了帷幕。
The beginning of the end of the end
of the beginning has begun.
一场哀伤的终曲，在这坏掉走音的钢琴上奏响，
A sad finale played off-key
on a broken-down saloon piano
在这被遗忘的鬼城的郊外，奏响。
in the outskirts of a
forgotten ghost town.
我宁愿不见证这么亵渎神明的事。
I'd rather not bear witness
to such blasphemy.
我也是。
Me neither.
布达佩斯大饭店变成了军队的营房。
The Grand Budapest
has become a troops' barracks.
这辈子我都不要进门了。
I shall never cross
its threshold again in my lifetime.
- 我也是。
- 我再也不要...
- Me neither.
- Never again shall I...
事实上，我们毕竟，现在就要进去了。
Actually, I think we might be
going in there right now after all.
迪米崔。
Dmitri.
阿加莎。
Agatha.
晚上好，戴斯高夫塔克西斯先生。
我是恰克先生。
Good evening, Mr. Desgoffe und Taxis.
I'm Monsieur Chuck.
我们为您和您的姐妹们预定了费迪南国王套间。
We've booked you and your sisters
into the King Ferdinand Suite.
晚上好，范.史可将军让我...
Good evening.
General von Shrecker asked me...
- 那是谁？
- 您说什么？
- Who's that?
- I beg your pardon?
我想那个姑娘拿着我的画呢。
借过。
I think that girl's got my picture.
Excuse me.
- 六楼。
- 等一下。
- Six.
- Hold it.
六楼。
Six.
门德尔先生恭贺您。
Compliments of Herr Mendl.
不好意思。
Excuse me.
你在过去的一分半中
Have you seen a pastry girl
with a package under her arm
见过一个胳膊下夹着包裹的蛋糕妹吗？
in the last minute and a half?
见过。她刚刚和戴斯高夫塔克西斯先生一起上了电梯。
Yep. She just got on the elevator
with Mr. Desgoffe und Taxis.
谢谢。
Thank you.
不好意思，你是谁？
I'm sorry. Who are you?
- 奥拓，先生，新来的门童。
- 你培训得不合格。
- Otto, sir, the new Lobby Boy.
- You haven't been trained properly.
门童才不应该提供那样的信息。
A Lobby Boy never provides
information of that kind.
你就是一堵墙。懂了吗？
You're a stone wall. Understood?
画不错。
Pretty picture.
六楼到了。
Sixth floor.
拿着苹果的男孩在哪？
Where's Boy with Apple?
和你没关系！
None of your goddamn business!
我现在要一口气灭了你这个软蛋！
I'm going to blast your candy-ass
once and for all right now.
扔掉武器！
Drop your weapon!
- 停火！停火！
- 天啊！
- Cease fire! Cease fire!
- Whoa!
停下！
Stop it!
谁在打谁？
Who's shooting who?
那是古斯塔夫.H！逃逸的杀人犯和艺术品窃贼！
That's Gustave H!
The escaped murderer and art thief.
我已经把他逼到绝路了！
I've got him cornered!
那是迪米崔.戴斯高夫塔克西斯！
That's Dmitri Desgoffe und Taxis!
他杀了卡瓦斯副手，
He's responsible for the killing
of Deputy Kovacs,
瑟奇.X和他的跛脚姐姐，在加上他自己的妈妈！
Serge X and his club-footed sister,
plus his own mother!
谁也别动。
你们都要被抓起来。
Nobody move.
Everybody's under arrest.
窗户外的是谁？
Who's out the window?
阿加莎！
Agatha!
310-bis.
撑住！我来了!
Hang on! Here I come!
背面有什么东西...
Something's on the back of the...
阿加莎!
Agatha!
阿加莎！
- 你没事吧？
- 我没事。
- Are you all right?
- I think so.
画的背面有东西。
Something's on the
back of the picture.
她当然把一切都留给了古斯塔夫先生。
She left everything
to Monsieur Gustave, of course.
那座大宅，也就是路兹城，
The mansion, known as Schloss Lutz,
生产武器，药品和织物的工厂，
the factories, which produced
weapons, medicine and textiles,
一个重要的报社集团，
an important newspaper syndicate,
还有估计你们已经猜到的，
and perhaps you've already deduced
这座有名的，布达佩斯大饭店。
this very institution,
the Grand Budapest Hotel.
他指定我作为他的继承人，
He anointed me his successor,
战火未熄，我报效祖国，
and as the war continued,
I served my adopted country
在这张窄窄的桌前，对着隔壁屋子的墙工作。
from the narrow desk still found
against the wall in the next room.
他和他的信徒一样，
He was the same as his disciples,
缺乏安全感，虚荣，肤浅，金发，欲求不满。
insecure, vain,
superficial, blond, needy.
到最后，他甚至变成了富翁。
In the end he was even rich.
然而，他却没有继续变老。
He did not succeed, however,
in growing old.
"亲爱的诸位，我们聚集在此..."
"Dearly beloved,
we are gathered together..."
我亲爱的阿加莎也没有。
Nor did my darling Agatha.
我们的儿子，会在两年后，
She and our infant son
would be killed two years later
死于普鲁士流感。一种小到荒谬的疾病。
by the Prussian grippe.
An absurd little disease.
现在看来不过一个星期的事，
在那时，成千上万的人却死于这短短七天。
Today we treat it in a single week,
but, in those days many millions died.
在工作的第21天，
On the 21st day of the occupation,
那天早上，朱波罗卡正式的，
the morning
the independent state of Zubrowka
不再作为独立国家存在，
officially ceased to exist,
我们和古斯塔夫先生去路兹旅行。
we traveled
with Monsieur Gustave to Lutz.
顺便说一句，你之前问题的答案是，
In answer to your earlier question,
by the way,
当然。
of course.
零曾经问我，我是怎样卑微的进入了饭店行业。
Zero asked me about my humble
beginnings in the hotel trade.
我曾经也许一度是
I was, perhaps, for a time,
considered the best Lobby Boy
布达佩斯大饭店最好的门童。
we'd ever had at the Grand Budapest.
我想可以这么说。
I think I can say that.
总算有一位做得比我好的了。
This one finally surpassed me.
但必须一提，他有位优秀的老师。
Although, I must say,
he had an exceptional teacher.
是的。
Truly.
"这两位面泛潮红，天上的生子，从何而来，
"Whence came these two
radiant, celestial brothers,
"一瞬，合为一体，
"united, for an instant,
"当他们穿越我们窗外，
星光闪闪的高空时吗？
"as they crossed the stratosphere
of our starry window?
"一位从东而来，一位从西。"
"One from the East
and one from the West."
很好。
Very good.
不许和她调情。
Don't flirt with her.
我们为什么又在麦地停下了？
Why are we stopping
at a barley field again?
我觉得这些穿黑制服的很是死气沉沉。
I find these black
uniforms very drab.
唔，你们好啊，小伙子们。
我们正谈到你们呢。
Well, hello there, chaps.
We were just talking about you.
- 请出示证件。
- 永远荣幸之至。
- Documents, please.
- With pleasure, as always.
你们是第一批让我们正式
You're the first of the
official death squads
自我介绍的射击队。
to whom we've been
formally introduced.
你们好吗？
How do you do?
万变不离其宗，我说的没错吧？
Plus ?§a change, am I right?
那是三阶工人身份的移民签证，亲爱的。
That's a migratory visa with
stage three worker status, darling.
读一读。
Read this.
- 出来。
- 别动。
- Come outside.
- Now, stay there.
我向你保证，如果你动了他一根手指头，
I give you my word,
if you lay a finger on this man,
你会被不光彩地踢出部队。
I'll see you
dishonorably discharged,
锁在栅栏里，日落时就绞死。
locked up in the stockade
and hanged by sundown.
微弱的文明之光，
There are still faint
glimmers of civilization
仍存留在这野蛮的屠场里，这就是人性。
left in this barbaric slaughterhouse
that was once known as humanity.
你们这些肮脏的，该死的，满脸麻子的法西斯混蛋！
You filthy, goddamn,
pock-marked, fascist assholes!
他是他们中的一员。
He was one of them.
还能说些什么呢？
What more is there to say?
最后发生了什么？
What happened in the end?
最后他们把他射杀了。
In the end they shot him.
所以这一切，都归我了。
So it all went to me.
晚餐后，我们去领房间的钥匙，
After dinner, we went to collect
the keys to our rooms,
但简先生已经擅离职守了。
but Monsieur Jean had
abandoned his post.
我猜他把咱们都忘了。
I expect he's forgotten
all about us.
近年来，
In recent years, of course,
像布达佩斯大饭店这样的私有财产，
such properties and holdings
as the Grand Budapest
几乎无一例外，移交公有。
had with very few exceptions
become common property.
既然他与新政府协商的准确条文，
While the precise terms
of his negotiation
从未公开，
with the new government
had never been announced,
这也就成了公开的秘密，
the result was an open secret,
那就是，零.穆斯塔法用巨额财产，
Zero Moustafa had traded
a great and important fortune
购买了一座昂贵的，不再盈利的，破败饭店。
in exchange for one costly,
unprofitable, doomed hotel.
为什么？
Why?
仅仅是出于感伤吗？
Was it merely sentimental?
这有点超出我应该知道的范围，
也不符合我的性格，
It was quite forward of me
and a bit out of character,
但我想为了我的健康，
but I felt I must know,
我必须知道。
for my health, I suppose.
恕我一问。我希望这问题不会让你心烦。
Forgive me for asking.
I hope I haven't upset you.
不，当然不会。
No, of course not.
这仅仅是你和那个消逝的世界最后的联系，
Is it simply your last connection
to that vanished world,
还是和他的世界的联系呢？
在你看来？
his world, if you will?
他的世界？
His world?
不，我不这样认为。
No, I don't think so.
你看，我们的职业相同。
You see, we shared a vocation.
那没什么必要。
It wouldn't have been necessary.
我是为阿加莎保留这座饭店的。
No. The hotel I keep for Agatha.
我们在这里很快乐。
We were happy here.
哪怕就那么一会儿。
For a little while.
说实话，我想他的世界早在他涉足前，
To be frank, I think
his world had vanished
便已经消失殆尽。
long before he ever entered it.
但，在我看来，
But, I will say,
是肯定用神奇的光辉，留住了那份幻象。
he certainly sustained the illusion
with a marvelous grace.
- 你要上去吗？
- 不了，我想坐一会儿。
- Are you going up?
- No, I'll sit for a little while.
晚安。
Good night.
接下来的星期，
The next week,
我坐船去南美治疗，
I sailed for a cure in South America
开始了在国外长时间的漫游。
and began a long,
wandering journey abroad.
很多年，我都不曾回到欧洲。
I did not return to
Europe for many years.
那是一片迷人的废墟。
It was an enchanting old ruin.
Best watched using Open Subtitles MKV Player